A Finding Aid to the Donald Saff papers and Saff Tech Arts Records, circa 1710, 1800-2013 bulk 1965-2010, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Donald Saff papers and Saff Tech Arts records
circa 1710, 1800-2013
bulk 1965-2010
Archives of American Art
Saff, Donald, 1937-
Saff Tech Arts
AAA.saffdona
Archival Resource Key
31.8 Linear feet
9.82 Gigabytes
Donald Saff papers and Saff Tech Arts records measures 31.8 linear feet, and 9.82 Gigabytes, and dates from circa 1710, 1800-2013, bulk 1965-2010. Donald Saff's papers document his career as an artist, and contain professional records prior to the founding of Saff Tech Arts, including his tenure at University of South Florida and Graphicstudio. Also included are records and correspondence documenting consulting and other collaboration outside of Saff Tech Arts. The series includes biographical material, correspondence, professional records, writings, exhibition files, printed material, and artwork. Saff Tech Arts (later Saff & Co.) records includes correspondence, founding documents including funding, fabrication and supplies information, artist files documenting working relationships ranging from potential collaboration, to long-term fabrication and representation, regular business relationships such as Knoedler & Co., and legal and insurance information including leases and worksite assessments. The series includes correspondence, artist files, business records, and printed material including clippings and subject files. Some materials are in digital formats.
Biographical / Historical
Donald Jay Saff, born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1937, is an artist, art historian, and fabricator in Oxford, Maryland known for close collaboration with leading American artists on the fabrication of technically complex artworks. He was exposed to printmaking while an undergraduate at Queens College in 1959, where he earned a B.F.A., followed by a master's degree in art history from Columbia University in 1960, and a M.F.A from Pratt Institute in 1962, and an Ed.D. in studio art and art history from Columbia University in 1964. In 1964 Saff was awarded a Fulbright grant which allowed him to study and work in Urbino, Italy. As an artist Saff created work and exhibited regularly throughout the 1980s. Donald Saff married Ruth Saff in 1960 and they have two sons, Stephen and Jeffery Saff.
Donald Saff was the founder of Graphicstudio in 1968 at the University of South Florida, where he was also chairman of the visual arts department. The studio became known for innovating new printing processes, including helio relief and waxtype. In 1971, Saff became the founding dean of the College of Fine Arts and was awarded the rank of distinguished professor at the university in 1982. In 1986, the National Gallery in Washington announced it would create an archive for all the work of Graphicstudio, a great tribute to Saff's accomplishment. Saff worked with a number of notable artists at Graphicstudio, creating collaborative bonds that would lay the ground for working together on his next venture. In 1991 Saff established his studio Saff Tech Arts (later Saff and Company) in Oxford, Maryland, partially thanks to a loan from key collaborator Robert Rauschenberg. During the early years of Saff Tech Arts Donald Saff also served as a gallery director to Knoedler and Co., which hosted exhibitions for many Saff Tech Arts collaborations. Other frequent collaborators include Nancy Graves, Roy Lichtenstein, James Rosenquist, and James Turrell.
Saff was later named Dean emeritus by University of South Florida in 1989, and distinguished professor emeritus in 1996. In 1999, Saff was awarded the honorary degree of Doctor of Fine Arts. As work at Saff Tech Arts slowed down Donald Saff became open to other opportunities in the arts, including a stint as Director of Capital Projects of the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation, New York, in 2001, followed by the appointment to Senior Curator of Prints and Drawings in 2002.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as two series:
Series 1: Donald Saff Papers, circa 1710-2010 (9.6 Linear feet: Boxes 1-10, 33)
Series 2: Saff Tech Arts Records, circa 1970-2013 (22.2 Linear feet: Boxes 10-32, 34)
Scope and Contents
Donald Saff papers and Saff Tech Arts records measures 31.8 linear feet, and 9.82 Gigabytes, and dates from circa 1710, 1800-2013, bulk 1965-2010.
Donald Saff's papers document his career as an artist, and contain professional records prior to the founding of Saff Tech Arts, including his tenure at University of South Florida and Graphicstudio. Also included are records and correspondence documenting consulting and other collaboration outside of Saff Tech Arts. Biographical material includes printed resumes as well as a biographical scrapbook with a hand-written letter in Italian dated 1710 and a biographical listing from "Who's Who in American Art." Correspondence is largely professional with some personal correspondence including letters with other artists. Listed chronologically, followed by an alphabetical run, this correspondence represents Saff's activities while affiliated with the University of Southern Florida and Graphicstudio. Also included are letters of reference for former students, studio assistants, and other colleagues, as well as regarding Saff's own job searches. The professional records subseries encompasses Saff's career as an artist including information on various bodies of artwork particularly in printmaking. This series focuses on Saff's professional career before Saff Tech Arts including Graphicstudio, as well as professional work after the height of Saff Tech Arts including consulting and curatorial work for the Guggenheim Museum and the status of Saff's registered patents. The writings subseries includes correspondence and manuscript material regarding Saff's 1978 book Printmaking co-authored with Deli Sacilotto, as well as follow-up and writings submitted for a possible update and reprint in the mid-1990s. Also included are published articles on the collaboration process. The exhibition subseries includes Saff's solo and group shows as an artist, as well as shows focusing on him as a fabricator and collaborator including the unrealized Joint Venture: Donald Saff and the Art of Collaboration, which was scheduled to open in Fall of 2009 at the Brooklyn Museum. The printed material subseries contains printed material related to Donald Saff's life and career before and following Saff Tech Arts, focusing on him as an educator and artist and founder of Graphicstudio, and the legacy of the art collection Saff assembled. The artwork subseries includes various sketches and notes by Donald Saff, as well as a test print made for wither Saff or another artist.
Saff Tech Arts (later Saff & Co.) records includes correspondence, founding documents including funding, fabrication and supplies information, artist files documenting working relationships ranging from potential collaboration, to long-term fabrication and representation, regular business relationships such as Knoedler & Co., and legal and insurance information including leases and worksite assessments, and printed material including clippings and subject files. Correspondents are usually clients including collectors and galleries. Artist files document a range of interest and working relationships ranging from potential collaboration, to long-term fabrication partnerships including representation. Regular collaborators included Nancy Graves, Robert Rauschenberg, Roy Lichtenstein, James Turrell, and James Rosenquist. Materials include printed material, fabrication information, sales and consignments, exhibition planning, shipping documents, and damage and restoration documentation. Business records include inventory, sales and consignments including multiple artists, regular business relationships including Knoedler & Co., appointment books, fabrication schedules, employee timesheets, and legal and insurance documents including claims, disputes and leasing information, as well as the pursuit of trademarks on production techniques. Some materials are in digital formats.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2022 by Donald Saff.
Artists' studios; Fabricators -- Maryland; Artists -- Maryland; Printmakers; Sound recordings; Interviews; Rauschenberg, Robert, 1925-2008; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Graves, Nancy Stevenson, 1940-1995; Rosenquist, James, 1933-; Turrell, James; University of South Florida. Division of Fine Arts; Graphicstudio
- Donald Saff Papers, circa 1710-2010; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 9.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-10, 33; 9.18 Gigabytes ER001-ER009
  Scope and Contents
  Donald Saff's papers document his career as an artist, and contain professional records prior to the founding of Saff Tech Arts, including his tenure at University of South Florida and Graphicstudio. Also included are records and correspondence documenting consulting and other collaboration outside of Saff Tech Arts.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged as eight subseries:
  1.1: Biographical Material, circa 1710-2002, bulk 1965-2002
  1.2: Correspondence, circa 1965-2008
  1.3: Professional Records, circa 1968-2006
  1.4: Writings, circa 1966-2010
  1.5: Exhibition Records, circa 1950-2010
  1.6: Photographic Material, circa 1970-2002
  1.7: Printed Material, circa 1800-2009
  1.8: Artwork, circa 1970s-1990s
  - Biographical Material, circa 1710-2002; bulk 1965-2002; 1.1; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 1
    Biographical material includes printed resumes as well as a biographical scrapbook with a hand-written letter in Italian dated 1710 and a biographical listing from "Who's Who in American Art."
    - Biography and CV, circa 1969-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Biographical Scrapbook, circa 1710, 1965-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Who's Who in American Art, circa 1994-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, circa 1965-2008; 1.2; Archival Resource Key; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-3; .006 Gigabytes ER001
    Correspondence is largely professional with some personal correspondence including letter with other artists. Listed chronologically, followed by an alphabetical run, this correspondence represents Saff's activities while affiliated with the University of Southern Florida and Graphicstudio. Also included are letters of reference for former students, studio assistants, and other colleagues, as well as regarding Saff's own job searches.
    - Correspondence, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, circa 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, circa 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, circa 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, circa1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
    - Correspondence, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - Correspondence, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    - Correspondence, circa 1990-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Undated Correspondence, circa 1965-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Personal Correspondence, circa 1969-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - First Name, Unidentified, circa 1991-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Brenau University, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Stuart Beckerman, Landmarks Division, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Lantz Caldwell, circa 1992-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - Graphicstudio: Selected Memoranda, circa 1982-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Graphicstudio, Miscellaneous, circa 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Graphicstudio Sales Correspondence (Endick, Zeelander), circa 1989-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Mark Stock, circa 1993-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Martina Hamilton Gallery (Mappelthorpe Prints), circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Theo Wujcik, circa 1994-2000; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records; see ER001. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Theo Wujcik, Digital Photographs and Document, 2009; Archival Resource Key; .006 Gigabytes Six computer files (Folder ER001)
    - Walla Walla Foundry, circa 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Application, Academy of the Arts, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Application, Pratt Institute President Search, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Application, Yale School of Art Dean, circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Miscellaneous, circa 1990-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Michael Harrigan, circa 1991-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Tomas Lopez, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Gifts, RISD Equipment Donation, Teaching, circa 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Gifts, Guggenheim Museum, circa 2000-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Gifts, National Arts Club Benefit Artwork Donation, Cigar Box, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Professional Records, circa 1968-2006; 1.3; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 3-4; .001 Gigabytes ER002
    The professional records subseries encompasses Saff's career as an artist including information on various bodies of artwork particularly in printmaking. This series focuses on Saff's professional career before Saff Tech Arts including Graphicstudio, as well as professional work after the height of Saff Tech Arts including consulting and curatorial work for the Guggenheim Museum and the status of Saff's registered patents.
    - Art Business Records, Saff Artwork and Collection, Archival Resource Key
      - Breezes Portfolio, Printing and Sales, circa 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Fables Print Series, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Constellations Print Series, circa 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Rights and Reproductions (DJS Artwork), circa 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - DJS Artwork Inquiries, circa 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Inventory, Available Prints, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - DJS Artwork Inventory, Saff Collection, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - DJS Artwork Storage Inventory, Fine Arts Express, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Shipping Documents (DJS Artwork), circa 1981-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Donald and Ruth Saff Shipment, Sculpture from France, circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - University of Southern Florida and Graphicstudio, Archival Resource Key
      - USF Record of Leave, circa 1968-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - USF Travel, circa 1971-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - USF Travel, China Citizen Ambassador (1976, 1978), circa 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - USF Travel, circa 1985-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - USF Application for Sabbatical, circa 1973-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Conference: New Directions in Printmaking: The Technical Side (U. of Saskatchewan) (Apr. 23-25 1992), circa 1991-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - USF Strategic Plan (1985-1990), circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - USF Graphics Workshop: Statement of Edition, circa 1969-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Pyramid - J. Rosenquist - Edition of 6 Prints, circa 1976, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - USF Graphicstudio James Rosenquist, circa 1986-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - DJS Travel, circa 1988-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Graphicstudio Founders Day Celebration (Apr. 8, 1999), circa 1999-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - USF Retirement, circa 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
      - Graphicstudio Student-Made Birthday Card, circa 1986-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Mobius Design, Inc. (Stephen Saff), circa 1991-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Patent Registration, Archival Resource Key
      - Saidman Design Law Group, circa 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Patent for "Method for the Application of an Image to a Porous Substrate", circa 1996-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Guggenheim Museum, Senior Curator for Special Projects, Archival Resource Key
      - Correspondence, Thomas Krens, circa 2000-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence, SGRM Employment, circa 2002-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
      - SGRM Travel, Las Vegas, circa 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - SGRM Rauschenberg Archive, circa 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
      - SGRM Travel, Moscow, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - SGRM Travel, St. Petersburg, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Contract, Senior Curator for Special Projects, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - SGRM Consulting, Tom Wesselmann, circa 2006; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records; see ER002. (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Tom Wesselmann Exhibition Chronology, Digital Document, 2006; Archival Resource Key; .001 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER002)
  - Writings, circa 1966-2010; 1.4; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 4; 0.019 Gigabytes ER003-ER004
    The writings subseries includes corresponence and manuscript material regarding Saff's 1978 book Printmaking co-authored with Deli Sacilotto, as well as follow-up and writings submitted for a possible update and reprint in the mid-1990s. Also included are published articles on the collaboration process with various artists, as well as teaching materials and various guest lectures and interviews.
    - Correspondence, Book Publishers, circa 1978-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Printmaking Book Ideas, circa 1980s-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Printmaking: History and Process (1978) Holt, Rinehart & Winston, Correspondence, circa 1970-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Printmaking: History and Process Holt, Rinehart & Winston, Reprint Correspondence, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Printmaking: History and Process 2nd Edition, Harcourt Brace Jovanovich Correspondence, circa 1990-1996; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records; see ER003. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Printmaking: History and Process 2nd Edition, Digital Documents, 1994; Archival Resource Key; 0.018 Gigabytes Eighteen computer files (Folder ER003)
    - Teaching Materials, "History of the Print: A Prospectus", circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Teaching Materials, "History of Woodcut Printing", circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - DJS Guest Editor Art Journal Spring 1980, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Slide Lecture on Graphicstudio, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Essay, "Jim Dine: Youth and the Maiden", circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - USF Graphicstudio Artist Statement and Print by Donald J Saff, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "Conservation of Matter: Robert Rauschenberg's Art of Acceptance" Aperture Fall 1991, circa 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Essay, "Art in Academia: The Limitless Boundary", circa 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Essay, "Photograph as Palette" Aperture Correspondence, circa 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Lecture "The Printmaker, The Photographer" Smithsonian Institution (May 7 1992), circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Article, Ernest Cox Exhibition Catalog, USF Museum (Apr. 1992), circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Robert Rauschenberg: The Art of Collaboration and the ART of Collaboration: Contemporary Prints from the Lilja Collection" Azimuth Editions, 1994; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records; see ER004. (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
    - "Robert Rauschenberg: The Art of Collaboration and the ART of Collaboration: Contemporary Prints from the Lilja Collection" Manuscript, Digital Document, 1994; Archival Resource Key; .001 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER004)
    - Lecture "Graphicstudio: 3 Decades of Printmaking (Apr.21, 1993), circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Interview, Sculpture May/June 1994, circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Lecture, Harn Museum (Jan. 21, 1994), circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Lecture, Art Seminar Group (Sep. 27, 1994), circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Rauschenberg Exhibition Catalog, Fine Arts Mandarin Oriental (Mar. 1994), circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Lecture "Innovative Publisher" (Apr. 1995), circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Lecture, Graphicstudio USF (Sep. 1995), circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "John Blair Mitchell Interviews Donald Saff" Baltimore Museum Newsletter (Apr. 1996), Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Lecture "Art of Collaboration: Graphicstudio and Saff & Co." (June 1998) New York University, circa 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Essay on Roy Lichtenstein and Collaboration, circa 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Interview with Gail Stravitsky, circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 29)